Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 2 -- Letters to Franklin 1777 January-1778 March Mss.B.F85inventory02
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 March 6; A.L.S. 2p.; Bedaulx, Charles Frederic. Paris
    Expects to set out for America on the 8th inst. by order of Mr. Deane. Begs Franklin to recommend him to some of his friends in America; with such an aid cannot fail to be employed with distinction in the service of a country for which he is ready to give up blood and life; his fear of being confounded with officers who have been forced to leave their country.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1777 March 7; A.L.S. 2p.; Morris, Robert. Philadelphia
    Congress has adjourned from Baltimore to Philadelphia; judges the time improper, as Gen. IIowe is forming another expedition against Philadelphia. Militia lacks clothing; hopes they will negotiate the loan and send out the articles wanted; the produce of America, if it could only be exported freely, would soon discharge the debt.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 March 7; A.L.S. 3p.; Alexander, William. Dijon
    Concerning the contract between M. Dubourg and the Farmers General. The risk of the voyage to and from America. Recommends Franklin's friend from South Carolina to Messrs. John Black and Co., Bordeaux. Increase in the circulation of bank paper. The opinion of the Privy Councillor of the Empress of Russia that England will not get a man from that Empire; recruiting goes on heavily in Germany. Sends first volume of M. de Morveaux's Elements of Chemistry.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 March 7; L.S. 1p.; Wickes, Lambert. L'Orient
    Would be glad of a line from Franklin concerning his further destination; all ready to heave down and only waiting for good weather. If Capt. Nicholson can be spared, the sooner he comes the better. Informed that the Admiralty of Vannes will clear all their prizes out under the French colors.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 March 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Beaumont, Jean-Baptiste-Jacques Elie de
    Introducing his friend M. de Villiers, one of the most honoured members of the "Société d'Emulation." who does not think it possible to put his talents to a more noble or patriotic use than in making a bust of Franklin. Begs him to accord his friend this favor, and for himself desires Franklin's portrait to bang in his library among the friends of their country and humanity.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 March 8; A.L.S. 3p.; Rumsey, Nathan. Nantes
    Just received confirmation of the affair at Trenton and the particulars of Gen. Lee's being taken, as he will find by the enclosed Gazettes. Numbers of killed and wounded and prisoners. Movements of Congress. Gen. Lee's capture has greatly enraged the populace; Gen. Washington informed the enemy that if Gen. Lee was sent to England he would hereafter give no quarter. Order of Congress for 100 battalions to be enlisted for three years.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1777 March 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Concerning the purchase of M. Montieu's muskets. Sale of Capt. Soakly's brig recommended by Mr. Schweighauser.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 March 8; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Eagerness of many persons to fit out privateers; if Franklin can give cruising commissions, could soon have several at sea; if it is necessary to have an American present in any such enterprise, offers his services. News from America; capture of Gen. Lee true; details of their successes in New Jersey.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 March 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Beaumont, Jean-Baptiste-Jacques Elie de
    Introducing M. de Champigny, an officer of distinction and nephew of a man held in high esteem in years past, who wishes to lay before Franklin certain views which may be useful.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 March 10; A.L.S. 2p.; Wright, Elizabeth
    Concerning the case of young Mr.Platt; his efforts to obtain a trail; Lord Mansfield's opinion that if he should petition the King and take the oath of allegiance he would be set at liberty; the petition has been written and signed; her fear that they might have urged the young man to do wrong; wishes there had been time to consult Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 March 10; A.L.S. 2p.; Platt, Ebenezer Smith. Newgate. London
    Starting certain details which were not thought proper to be inserted in his case. Ineffectual efforts to obtain a trial; chances for and against his being set free.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1777 March 11; A.L.S. 1p.; Morris, Thomas. Nantes
    Informing him of the safe arrival of the ship Jenifer in 35 days from Baltimore with despatches for him, which the bearer, Capt. Hammond, will deliver.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 March 11; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Account of the business he proposes to enter into with Mr. Schweinghauser; begs Franklin to write a line to him relative to the proposed connection; flatters himself that the want of a proper establishment is the sole objection to a still closer union.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1777 March 11; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Business connected with loading The Count de Vergennes. Arrival of a little schooner express from Congress; the Captain and Mr. Rumsey gone to Paris. Rumor that General Washington has cut off the English retreat in New Jersey.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1777 March 11; A.L.S. 3p.; Dumas, St Jean Charles Guillaume Frederic
    Congratulating them on the American success in New Jersey; troubled at the capture of the brave General Lee. Memoir presented to the King by the English Ambassador, demanding the punishment of the Governor of St. Eustache for favoring the Americans, and ordering that the sale of arms to them shall cease. Recommends the sending of American news to the French Gazette of Leiden.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 March 11; A.L.S. 3p.; Penet, Pierre. Nantes
    The bearer, Mr. Rumsey, accompanies Capt. Hammond to Paris with letters from the Secret Committee at Philadelphia. All the transactions confided to him have been carried out with the greatest exactitude. Mr. Thomas Morris busy from morning to night. The sale of prizes at L'Orient conducted with prudence and discretion.
  - Franklin and Deane, 1777 March 12; A.L.S. 3p.; Lee, Arthur. Victoria
    Greatly elated over the joyful intelligence enclosed; the militia so exasperated by the past cruelty of the enemy that they fought with irresistible fury; afraid Gen. Lee is a prisoner; loss sustained by the enemy; upwards of a thousand of the prisoners in New York have died of famine and cruel treatment; destruction by these "Saracen invaders" of the philosophical apparatus at Princeton. Awaiting the arrival of Count de Grimaldi with news from the Court. Means he has taken to publish an account of the late intelligence in various countries, especially among the German troops. Considers Holland has broken her strict neutrality by agreeing to let the mercenaries, notoriously hired to desolate the States of America, have a passage. If Mr. Deane should go to Amsterdam, advises him to be on his guard against Mr. Paul Wentworth.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 March 12; A.L.S. 1p.; Barbeu-Dubourg, Jacques.
    Begging him to send by bearer the original treaty between the Farmers-General and himself, which he forgot, and which he has actual need of.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 March 12; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Wilkinson, William. Paris
    Informing Dr. Franklin that he knows a gentleman going to London who may be depended on to carry any letters there carefully; if Dr. Franklin will state when the letters will be ready, he will call for them himself.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 March 13; A.L.S. 1p.; Baud, -----. Paris
    A person, concerning whom M. le due de la Rochefoucauld could furnish information, desired him to make certain propositions to Franklin which he believes would cause him pleasure; requests the honor of an interview.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 March 13; A.L.S. 1p.; Wickes, Lambert. L'Orient
    Extraordinary orders he has just received from the Commissary of the above port to get his ship cleaned, put everything on board and leave immediately and not to enter any French port again. Wishes to know the meaning of this order and how he is to proceed.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 March 15; A.L.S. 2p.; Small, Alexander. St.Philips, Minorca
    Thinks Britain is hurting herself by an enormous increase of her debt, but considers the war a just scourge on America for her excessive luxury and dissipation, which will be checked now before too late. Paper he has written and sent to Sir J. Pringle on the ventilation of hospitals; will send Franklin a copy and begs him to put the finishing touches to it.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 March 15; L.S. 2p.; Wickes, Lambert. L'Orient
    Concerning the proceedings against him of Mr. Gonnett, Commissary of the Port; desires Franklin's instructions; his anxiety to leave a place where he has received such treatment; no conduct on his part has merited such behavior.
    Printed in Hale's Franklin in France, I, 119.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1777 March 15; L. 3p.; The Farmers-General
    Are now ready to make and sign the contract with the Commissioners from Congress on the basis of the latter's offer to deliver to the Farmers-General, in France, 4,000 bales of tobacco at a net price of 8 francs per pound. The Farmers-General will advance 2,000,000 francs as payment. Cite the articles of agreement.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 March 15; A.L. in 3d P.; Paulze, Jacques. Paris
    Sending Franklin a draft of the contract proposed by M. Grand. If Franklin and his colleague approve the provisions thereof, they are requested to notify M. Paulze.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 March 16; A.L.S. 2p.; Lee, Arthur. Vittoria
    In receipt of an answer through the Duke of Grimaldi; the reasons for wishing him not to come to Madrid are insuperable; amount of aid Spain is willing to render the Colonies. Arranging with the house of Gardoqui for three vessels of supplies to be despatched as soon as possible. Reports of Gen. Washington's offer to exchange three Hessian officers. The Duke of Grimaldi's opinion relative to the Americans' right to demand vessels betrayed to England, and to Holland's right to give the German mercenaries a passage through their country.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 March 16; A.L.S. 2p.; Lombart, Louis-Pierre Penot, chevalier de la Neuville. Paris
    Emboldened by a desire of glory and a wish to be serviceable to a nation fighting for her liberty, he and his brother have decided to go to Boston and offer thier services. His rank as major, his youth, good-will, health and enthusiasm, all the recommendations he has; if he cannot get the rank of colonel he will take the field as a volunteer.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 March 17; A.L.S. 2p.; Gastebois, ------. Lauzun
    In receipt of a letter from the Duc de Duras, who informs him that he asked Franklin for two companies for his (Gastebois') two sons, and that Franklin inquired if they spoke English; at this precise moment they do not, but promises that they shall speak it in three months, if that is the only obstacle; his sons worthy of Franklin's protection.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 March 18; L.S. 1p.; Debrissac de Saxey, —. Saint Quentin
    Congratulating himself on the happpiness of meeting Franklin during his last stay in Paris; reminds him of his promise to give them orders when he receives his commissions from America. The pleasure he derives from Franklin's success and prosperity.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1777 March 18; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Shipping news.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 March 19; A.L.S. 2p.; Morris, Thomas. Nantes
    Presumes by this time Franklin has received the sundry despatches from America by Captain Hammond; will be greatly obliged for any intelligence Franklin may think proper to communicate. Arrival of the ship Versailles, 40 days from Boston, which brought the enclosed letter; very important that it be safely delivered as directed. Report of Gen. Howe having sent a flag of truce to General Washington, requesting a cessation of arms for a few days.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 March 21; A.L.S. 1p; Gordon, William. Jamaica Plain Mass
    Troubles him with a packet for their friend, Dr. Price; asks him to peruse the letters and papers before forwarding; wished to put both parties out of conceit with Mr.Hutchinson, a man whose only supporters should be "two upright posts with one across it". Continental lottery likely to succeed. Ten thousand would probably go off in Massachusetts very soon.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 March 21; A.L.S. 1p.; Barbeu-Dubourg, Jacques.
    Begs him to accord an audience to the Baron de Fray whose demands are very reasonable and his offers of service very important.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 March 21; A.L.S. 3p.; Baudin, François. St. Martin, Isle de Rè
    Writes to offer his services in the above-mentioned isle, which by its position is suitable for a market of commodities. The excellent quality of the brandy made in the island. Begs Franklin for some orders; asks only the ordinary commission.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 March 24; N. in 3d P. 1p.; Messrs. de Germany and Girardot
    Request Dr. Franklin to send them his reply to a letter from Strasbourg which they received for him.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1777 March 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Morris, Robert. Philadelphia
    Commanded by Congress to transmit copies of their resolve of the 13th inst. to their ministers and agents abroad; many gentlemen in the service of America useless, owing to ignorance of the language; thinks this the best means to save others the charge and trouble of the voyage as well as the mortification of being disappointed.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 March 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Extremely uneasy at not hearing from him relative to Mr. Schweighauser's proposals; afraid his silence will create an unfavorable impressian. Beset with politicians who are forever asking for news. Arrival of an order from the English Ambassador which would have obliged Major Lutterloh's return to his regiment had he not already embarked.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1777 March 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Arrival of supplies for The Comte de Vergennes; officers applying for passage; desires instructions as to answering them.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 March 26; A.L.S. 2p.; La Rochefoucauld, Louis-Alexandre, duc de La Roche-Guyon et de. Paris
    Begs Franklin to cast his eyes over the translation of the Constitution of Delawarc and send it to him at Rouen, with the corrections, so that it may be published on his return; if he has a copy of the Constitution of Maryland begs him to send it also; he will translate that as well as the Constitution of Virginia. Inquires if he has heard whether the different Colonies have accepted at Act of Confederation just as it is or with changes.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 March 27; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Concerning a plan proposed to him by M. Dubourg; referred him to Franklin; would first wish to know Franklin's opinion of Mr. Schweighuser's proposals.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1777 March 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Concerning the increase in the cargo of the The Comte de Vergennes.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1777 March 28; L. 4p.; Morris, Robert. Philadelphia
    Gen. Howe's army in the Jerseys inactive and greatly distressed for want of forage and fresh provisions; thinks they will not be content with their situation much longer; desertions frequent. The summing up of what General Washington has done with an army half the size of the enemy's and consisting chiefly of raw militia. The bad results attending short enlistments; Congress busy reforming their systems respecting the army; this being done, has great hopes for the summer, especially if Franklin effects a European war to employ the British navy. Possibility of Gen. Howe attacking Philadelphia; if he does get it, prophesies that it will prove his ruin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 March 28; A.L.S. 1p.; Grenus, Col Tissot. Geneva
    Expressing his sincere appreciation of the conversation he had with Franklin; if Franklin's sons should visit the country where he is at present, he would like to show his appreciation fo thier relationship to such a great man.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 March 28; A.L.S. 1p.; Jousserant, — de. Route de Bordeaux
    Offering his services to the colonies; his experience as assistant major of grenadiers.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 March 29; A.L.S. 2p.; Alexander, William. Dijon
    A story is current that the British ministry have applied to France to have Mr. Deane delivered up, on the pretext that he was concerned in the burning of Portsmouth; proves, by quoting a precedent, that they do not need to comply with this request.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 March 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Application for a passage to America by Capt. Paddack who will also serve as a pilot.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 March 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Sr
    All well and in good spirits in spite of the war. His son John anxious to go to France and see his brother, who might help him to some employ.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 March 29; A.L.S. 3p.; Wright, Patience. London
    Mr. Platt's marriage to her daughter and their return to America have already been laid before Franklin. A dream she had several years ago about Dr. Franklin, which so far is only half fulfilled, but she believes it will be completed. Intends coming to France to make a bust of Franklin in wax; also one of the Queen, and any others he may approve of.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 March 30; A.L.S. 1p.; Deane, Silas, 1737-1789
    Enclosing a letter from Mr. Williams which appears to have been opened. Reminds him of the letter and deposition for Lord Stormont and the memorial for the Portugal Ambassador.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 March 30; A.L. 4p.; Cooper, Samuel. Boston
    Anxious to hear from Franklin. Welcome arrival of arms, powder, woolens, etc., from France. Burning of some stores left at Peekskill by the enemy. Account of skirmish not far from Amboy, the enemy retreating with a loss of 500 killed, wounded and taken. Gen. Washington thinks it probable that Philadelphia will be attacked and a considerable part of the army in Canada will come down the St. Lawrence river to join him. Expects Washington will soon be able to take the field with an adequate force. Price of everything greatly advanced. Lottery tickets have a surprisingly rapid sale. Cruelties perpetrated by the enemy have increased the numbers and zeal on their side. France cannot long avoid a war with Britain; she never had a fairer opportunity for taking a decisive part. Sends this by Mr. Cushing, a young man much esteemed at home, who goes to France on business.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 March 31; A.L.S. 2p.; Arrenberg, Reinier. Rotterdam
    In his quality of 2d Secretary of the Physical Society at Rotterdam he has long wanted to send Franklin the two volumes of the "Actes de la Société". In his character of journalist is anxious to know some one who can give him some news of America. Holland's interest in and sympathy with America renders it necessary to procure real American news; willing to pay such a person well.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1777 March 31; L.S. James Bowdoin, President. 3p.; The Council of Massachusetts Bay. Boston
    Copy of letter V, 75. They have employed Mr. Thos. Cushing, Jr., to carry three letters to him from the Secret Committee and to await his orders.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, N. in 3d P. 1p.; Wilkinson, William. Paris
    Requests Dr. Franklin to send him the letter for Nantes, as he is about to leave Paris for the place.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 April 1; A.L.S. 1p.; Penet, Pierre. Nantes
    Announcing the arrival of two ships; will forward any letters there may be for him. Mr. Williams still at Nantes; according to instructions, continues to pay him all the money that he asks for. His interest and zeal in the service.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 April 2; A.L.S. 2p.; Ingenhousz, Jan
    Franklin's letters delayed. Sets out for Ratisbon on April 12 and will remain there with the Prince of Taxis during May and a part of June; his plan to go from there to Holland, England and France, if his Royal mistress permits; his desire to see Franklin; the Emperor's departure for Paris is a convincing proof of a peaceful disposition among the European powers.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1777 April 2; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Arrival from Boston of Capt. Adams who has set off with his packets for Paris. Has begun the inventory.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 April 2; A.L.S. 2p.; Barberie, — La. Paris
    Reminds Franklin of his promise to give his son some letters of recommendation should he enter the service of the Colonies; the young man expects to leave with M. de Galvan, and he would count it a real kindness if Franklin would procure for him the acquaintance of his friends.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 April 5; A. L. 2p.; Feutry, Aimé Ambroise Joseph
    Will call on Franklin the next day; outlines of a letter which he begs Franklin to write to Madame Hubert in his (Feutry's) favor, containing a request for an interview with M. Necker.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 April 5; A. L. S. 3p.; Burdett, P. P. Rastatt
    Wrote Franklin on his arrival in France at the particular request of their Highnesses, the Prince and Princess of Baden; imagines the letter never reached him. Is himself a strong well-wisher for the Amercian cause; has inspired a certain officer in the service of his Serene Highness with a strong desire of embarking on the American side; his friend's fitness for the work; recommends him to Franklin. Would be unwilling to have all the subject of this letter known to his Prince.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 April 5; A. L. S. 1p.; Montée, ------
    Request for his son to enter the American army.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 April 7; A. L. S. 1p.; Feutry, Aimé Ambroise Joseph
    Sending him a copy of various mémoirs relating to instruments of war. His pleasure in knowing a great man like the Marquis de Puységur, Lieutenant-General; the Count d'Heronville honors him likewise with his kind interest.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 April 7; A. L. S. 8p.; Alexander, William. Dijon
    The bearer of this is M. de Montarché, formerly Intendant of St. Domingo. Encloses his answer to M. Dubourg with his contract; if he goes into the affair, mentions the terms he would be willing to accept and his reasons for it. Story of a new treaty being arranged between France and Britain. Discusses the absurd habit of the commanders of fleets engaging in the center of their squadron, where they can neither see nor know what passes at any distance. "American plan of debauching seamen to carry in ships" explained in Lloyd's book. Has seen his correspondence with Lord Howe in the English papers and likes it much. Compares loss by sickness and desertion in ancient and modern warfare. His views on the opening campaign in America.
  - to the American Commissioners, 1777 April 7; A.L.S. 3p.; Boux, Jacques.
    Concerning the building of certain ships; advantages of the port of L'Orient. Strict espionage maintained on every side by the Marshal's Court.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 April 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Feutry, Aimé Ambroise Joseph
    Sending Franklin a dozen of his new fables which appeared with twenty others in the second volume of his "d'Opuscules poetiques et philologiques". Considers the day he met Franklin the happiest of his life.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 April 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Rybot, C. Paris